PETER SZOLOVITS: So
today's topic is workflow,
and this is something that--
a topic that I didn't
realize existed
when I started
working in this area,
but I've had my nose
ground and ground into it
for many decades.
And so finally, it has
become obvious to me
that it's something
to pay attention to.
So here's an
interesting question.
Suppose that your goal
in the kind of work
that we're doing in this class
is to improve medical care--
not an unreasonable goal.
So how do you do it?
Well, we had an idea
back in the 1970s
when I was getting
started on this, which
was that we wanted to
understand what the world's best
experts did and to
create decision support
systems by encapsulating
their knowledge about how
to do diagnosis, how to
do prognosis and treatment
selection, in order to
improve the performance
of every other doctor
who was not a world class
expert by allowing the world
class expertise captured
in a computer system to
help people figure out
how to do better--
so to make them more accurate
diagnosticians, more efficient
therapists, et cetera.
And the goal here was
really to bring up
the average performance
of everybody
in the health care system.
So we used to say things
like, bring everybody
practicing medicine closer
to the level of practice
of the world class experts.
Now, that turned out not
to be what was important.
And so there was another idea
that came along a little bit
later that said, well,
it's not really so much
the average performance
of doctors that's bad.
It's the subaverage performance
that's really terrible.
And so if you're subaverage
performance leads
to your patients dying, but your
above average performance only
makes a moderate difference
in their outcomes,
then it's clearly more important
to focus on the people who
are the worst doctors and to
get them to act in a better way.
And thus, was born the
idea of a protocol that
says, let's treat similar
patients in similar ways.
And the value of that is
to reduce the variance--
so improve average
versus reduce variance.
So which of these is better?
Well it depends on
your loss function.
So as I was suggesting, if your
loss function is a symmetric so
that doing badly or
doing below average
is much worse than
doing above average
is much better, than this
protocol idea of reducing
variance is really important.
And this is pretty much what
the medical system has adopted.
So I wanted to try to
help you visualize this.
Suppose that on some
arbitrary scale of 0 to 8,
we have an usual, normal
distribution, of on the left
the base behaviors--
so this is how people, on
average, normally behave--
we assume that there's something
like a normal distribution.
So here is a world class
expert whose performance
is up at 6 or 7
and here's the dud
of a doctor whose performance
is down between 0 and 1.
And the average doctor
is just shy of 4.
So here are two scenarios.
Scenario one is that we
improve these guys performance
by just a little bit.
So we improve it by
0.1 performance points,
I think is what I've
done in this model.
versus another
approach, which is
suppose we could cut
down the variance
dramatically so that this same
normal distribution becomes
narrower.
Its average is still in
exactly the same place,
but now there are
no distant outliers.
So there aren't doctors
who perform a lot worse,
and there aren't doctors who
perform a lot better either.
Well, what happens in that case?
Well, you have to look
at the cost function.
So if you have a cost
function like this that says,
that somebody's performing at
the 0 level has a cost of 1.
Whereas somebody
performing at the 8 level
has a cost of almost 0, and
it's exponentially declining
like this, so that the
average performance has
a much lower cost than the
average between the worst
performance and the
best performance.
So this suggests that,
if you could bunch people
into this region of performance,
that your overall costs
would go down.
And, in fact-- this is a
purely hypothetical model that
I've built--
but if you do the
calculations, you
discover that for the
base distribution,
here is the
distribution of costs.
For the slightly
improved distribution,
you get a cost, which is
1,694 versus 781, again,
in arbitrary units.
But if you manage to
narrow the distribution,
you can get the total cost
down to less than what
you do by improving the average.
Now, this is not a proof,
but this is the right idea.
The proof is
probably in the fact
that medical systems
have adopted this,
and have decided that getting
all doctors to behave more
like the average doctor is the
best practical way of improving
medical care.
Well, how do we narrow the
performance distribution?
So one way is by having
guidelines and protocols where
you have some learned body who
prescribes appropriate methods
to diagnose and treat patients.
So what happens is, for example,
the article here from November
of 2018, a report of the
American College of Cardiology,
the American Heart Association
Task Force on Clinical Practice
Guidelines, and this
has been adopted
by this cornucopia of
three and four letter
abbreviated organizations.
And it's a guideline
on the management
of blood cholesterol.
So as you know, having high
cholesterol is dangerous.
It can lead to heart
attacks and strokes,
and so there is a
consensus that it would be
good to lower that in people.
So these guys went about
this by gathering together
a bunch of world
experts and saying,
well, how do we do this?
What do we promulgate
as the appropriate way
to care for patients
with this condition?
And the first thing
they did is they
came up with a
color coded notion
of how strong the recommendation
a certain recommendation
should be And
another color coded
or shaded level of certainty
in that recommendation.
So, for example, if you say
something is in class 1,
so it's a strong
recommendation, then
you use words like is
recommended, or is indicated,
useful, effective, beneficial,
should be performed, et cetera.
If it's in class 2,
where the benefit is
much greater than
the risk, then you
say things like it's reasonable,
it can be useful, et cetera.
If the benefit is maybe equal
to or a little bit better
than the risk, you say
waffle words, like might be
reasonable, may be considered.
If there is no benefit,
in other words,
if it roughly equals
the risk, then you say,
it's not recommended.
And if the risk is
greater than the benefit,
then you say things like
it's potentially harmful,
causes harm, et cetera.
So if you were giving
a recommendation
on whether to spray
disinfectant down your lungs,
you might put that in red and
say, this is not recommended.
And then here,
this shading coding
is basically how
good is the evidence
for this recommendation.
So the best evidence,
the level A,
is high-quality evidence from
multiple randomized controlled
clinical trials,
or a meta-analyses
of a high-quality RCTs,
or RCTs corroborated
by high-quality
registry studies.
And then we go down
to level C, which
is consensus of expert opinion
based on clinical experience,
but without any sort
of formal analysis.
So if you look at this
particular document
on cholesterol it
says, well, here
are the recommendations
on the measurement
of LDL and non-HDL cholesterol.
And they say here,
the confidence
and the recommendation
is one, and it's based
on B and our level of evidence.
And it says, in adults who
are 20 years or older and not
on lipid-lowering
therapy, measurements
of either a fasting or a
non-fasting blood-- dot,
dot, dot.
So you could read this
in the notes later.
But notice that there are
high force recommendations.
There are lower force
recommendations,
and each recommendation
is also shading
coded to tell you what
the strength of evidence
is for this kind
of recommendation.
Here's just another example.
This is secondary
atherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease prevention.
So this is for somebody
who's already ill,
and it's a bunch
of recommendations.
If you're over 75 years
of age, or younger
with a clinical case of
coronary vascular disease,
then high intensity
statin therapy
should be initiated or
continued with the aim
of achieving a 50% or greater
reduction in LDLC and et
cetera.
So again, a whole bunch of
different recommendations.
Once again, the strength of the
recommendation-- by the way,
this is just the first
page of a couple of pages--
and the quality of
evidence for it.
So this is very
much the way that
learned societies are
now trying to influence
the practice of medicine in
order to reduce the variance
and get everybody to
behave in a normal way.
You've probably seen articles
about Atul Gawande, who's
a surgeon here in Boston, and
he's gotten publicly famous
for advocating checklists.
And he says, for
example, if you're
a surgeon, you should act
like an airline pilot,
that before you take
off in the airplane,
you go through a
sanity checklist
to make sure that all the
systems are working properly,
that all the switches
are set correctly,
which in a surgical
setting would be things
like you have all the right
necessary equipment available,
that you know what to do in
various potential emergencies,
et cetera.
So here are their take-home
messages, which makes sense.
Here, I've abstracted
these from the paper
that has all of these details.
So number one, you
go, well, duh--
in all individuals, emphasize
a heart healthy lifestyle
across the life course.
That seems not
terribly controversial,
and in people who
are already diseased,
reduce low-density lipoprotein
with high-intensity therapy
by statins.
And in very high risk
ASCVD, use a threshold
of 70 milligrams per
deciliter, et cetera.
So these are the
summary recommendations.
And the hope is that doctors
reading these sorts of articles
come away from them convinced
and will remember that they're
supposed to act this way
when they're interacting
with their patients.
This is a flow chart,
again, abstracted
from that paper by them
which says, everybody,
you should emphasize
a healthy lifestyle.
And then depending on
your age, depending
on what your estimate
of lifetime risk is,
you wind up in
different categories.
And these different categories
have different recommendations
for what you ought to
do with your patients.
This is for
secondary prevention.
So it's a similar flow chart for
people who are already diseased
and not just at risk.
And then for people at very
high risk for future events,
which is defined
by these histories
and these high-risk
conditions, these
are the people who fall
into that second flow chart
and should be treated that way.
Now, by the way, I
didn't make a poll,
so I'll give you the answer.
But it's interesting to ask.
So when papers like
this get published,
how well do doctors
actually adhere to these?
And the answer turns
out to be not very well,
and it takes many, many
years before these kinds
of recommendations are
taken up by the majority
of the community, so even
very, very uncontroversial
recommendations.
For example, I think
20 years ago there
was a recommendation that said
that anybody who's had a heart
attack should be treated, even
if they're now asymptomatic,
with beta blockers.
Because in various
trials, they showed
that there was a 35% reduction
in repeat heart attacks
as a result of this treatment.
It took, I think, over a dozen
years before most doctors
were aware of this
and started making
that kind of recommendation
to their patients.
There's something
called the AHRQ,
the Agency for Health
Research and Quality.
And until the current
administration,
they ran a national
guideline clearinghouse
that contained myriad of
these guidelines, published
by different authorities,
and was available for people
to download and use.
There's been an attempt
by Guideline Central
to take over some of these roles
since the government shutdown
the government run one, and
they have about 2,000 guidelines
that are posted on their site.
And these are some
of the examples.
So risk reduction
of prostate cancer
with drugs or
nutritional supplements,
stem cell transplantation
in multiple myeloma,
in myelodysplastic syndromes
and acute myeloid
leukemia, et cetera.
And then they also publish
a bunch of risk calculators
that say--
I don't know what the 4T
score is for heparin-induced
thrombocytopenia--
but there are tons
of these as well.
So there's a clearinghouse
of these things.
And you, as a practicing
doctor, can go to these.
Or your hospital can
decide that they're
going to provide these
guidelines to their doctors,
and either encourage,
or in some cases,
coerce them to use the
guidelines in order
to determine what
their activity is.
Now, notice that this is a
very top-down kind of activity.
So it's typically done by
these learned societies that
bring together
experts to cogitate
on what the right thing
to do is, and then they
tell the rest of the
world how to do it.
But there's also a kind
of bottom-up activity.
So there is something
called a "care plan."
Now, a care plan is
really a nursing term.
So if you hang
out at a hospital,
the thing you discover is that
the doctors are evanescent.
They appear and disappear.
They're like
elementary particles,
and they're not
around all the time.
The people who are
actually taking care of you
are the nurses.
And so the nurses have
developed a set of methodologies
for how to ensure that
they take good care of you,
and one of them
is the development
of these care plans.
And then what
clinical pathways are
is an attempt to take the
care plans that nurses
use in taking care
of individuals
and to generalize from
those and say, well,
what are the typical ways in
which we take care of patients
in a particular cohort?
So I'm going to talk a
little bit about that,
and one of the papers I gave
you as an optional reading
for today is about
cow paths, which
are these attempts to build
generalizations of care plans.
So this is a care plan from the
Michigan Center for Nursing,
which is an educational
organization that
tries to help nurses figure
out how to be good nurses.
I was very amused when
I was looking for this.
I ran across a video, which is
some experienced nurse talking
about how you build
these care plans.
And she sort of says, well,
when you're in nursing school,
you learn how to build these
very elaborate carefully
constructed care plans.
When you're actually
practicing as a nurse,
you'll never have
time to do this.
And so you're going to do a
rough approximation to this.
And don't worry about it.
But for now, satisfy your
professors by doing these
exercises correctly.
So take a look at this.
So there are a bunch of columns.
The leftmost one
says assessment.
So this is objective,
subjective,
and medical diagnostic data.
So the objective data is this
patient has gangrene-infected
left foot--
not a good thing, an open
wound, et cetera, et cetera.
Subjective data, the patient
said the pain is worse
when walking and turning.
She dreads physical
therapy, and she
wishes she did not have
to be in this situation--
surprise.
But that's definitely
subjective.
You can't see external
evidence of that.
The nursing diagnosis
is that this patient
has impaired tissue
integrity in reference
to the wound and the
presence of an infection.
Now, that diagnosis actually
comes with a kind of guideline
about how to make
that diagnosis.
In other words, in order
to be able to put that down
on the care plan,
she has to make sure
that characteristics
of the patient
satisfy certain criteria
which are the definition
of that diagnosis.
The patient outcomes--
so this is the goals
that the nurse is
trying to achieve.
And notice, there
are five goals here.
One is that the patient will
report any altered sensation
of pain at the tissue impairment
between January 23 and 24.
So this is a very specific goal.
It says, the
patient will tell me
that they feel
better, that there's
a change in their feeling
in their infected left foot.
They will understand the plan to
heal tissue and prevent injury.
So there's a patient
education component.
They will describe measures to
protect and heal the tissue,
including wound care by 124.
So notice, this is the
patient describing to you
what you are planning to do
for them, in other words,
demonstrating an understanding
of what the plan is
and what's likely
to happen with them.
Experience a wound decrease
that decreases in size
and has increased
granulation tissue,
and achieve functional
pain goal of 0
by 124 per the
patient's verbalization.
So when they come
in and they ask you
on that pain scale, are
you at a 0, or a 10,
or somewhere in
between, the goal
is that the patient
will say, I'm at a 0,
in other words, no pain.
Now, what are the interventions?
Well, these are the
things that the nurse
plans to do in order to
try to achieve those goals.
And then the rationale
is an explanation
of why it's reasonable to expect
those interventions to achieve
those goals.
And the evaluation
of outcomes says,
what criteria or what are
the actual outcomes for what
we're trying to achieve?
So that gets filled
in later, obviously,
then when the plan is made.
So if you look at a
website like this,
there are templated care plans
for many, many conditions.
You can see that I'm
only up to C in an A to Z
listing from this one website,
and there are plenty of others.
But there is an admission care
plan, adult failure to thrive,
alcohol withdrawal, runny
nose, altered cardiac output,
amputation.
I don't know what
an anasarca is--
anemia, angina, anticoagulant
care, et cetera.
So there are tons of
different conditions
that different
patients fall into,
and this is a way of trying to
list the template care plans.
Now, this paper is
kind of interesting,
by Yiye Zhang and colleagues.
And what they did
is they said, well,
let's take all these
care plans and let's
try to build a machine learning
system that learns what
are the typical patterns that
are embedded in those care
plans.
But they didn't
start with the plans.
This is retrospective analysis.
So what they started with
is the actual records
of what was done
to each patient.
And so the idea is that
you get treatment data
from the electronic
health record.
Then you identify patient
subgroups from that data,
and then you mine for
common treatment patterns.
And you have medical
experts evaluate these,
and these then become
clinical pathways,
which are this generalization
of the care plans
to particular
subpopulations of patients.
So the idea is that they
define a bunch of abstractions.
So they say, look,
an event is a visit.
So, for example,
for an outpatient,
anything that happens to you
during one visit to a doctor
or to a hospital.
So it's a set of procedures,
a set of medications,
a set of diagnoses.
And by the way,
they were focusing
on people with kidney disease
as the target population
that they were looking at.
So then they say,
OK, individual events
are going to be abstracted into
these supernodes, which capture
a unique combination of
associations of events
associated with some visit.
So you might worry that this
is going to be combinatorial,
because there are many possible
combinations of things.
And that is, in fact,
a bit of a problem,
I think, in their analysis.
So now, you have
these supernodes,
and then each patient
has a visit sequence,
which is a time-ordered
list of the supernodes.
So every time you
go see your doctor,
you have one new supernode.
And so you have a
time series of these.
And then they do
the following thing.
They say, gee, when we talk
to our doctors and nurses,
they tell us that
they care mostly
about what happened at the last
visit that the patient had.
But they also care
a little bit less,
but they still care about what
happened at the visit previous
to that, but not so much about
history going further back.
And so they say, well,
in a Markov chain,
we only have things depend on
the last node in the Markov
chain.
So let's change
the model here so
that we will combine
pairs of visits
into nodes so that each
node in the Markov chain
will represent the last two
visits that the patient had.
So this could, again, cause
some combinatorial problems.
But here's the image
that they come up with.
So there are individual items.
Is it a hospital visit,
an office visit, a visit
for the purpose of education?
Are you in chronic kidney
disease stage four?
Was an ultrasound done?
Were you given ACE inhibitors?
Were you given
diuretics, et cetera?
So these are all the
data that we mentioned.
They treat that as a bag.
And then they say,
OK, we're going
to identify all the bags that
have the same exact content.
An asterisk, they didn't
look, for example,
at the dose of medication
that you were given,
only which medication it was.
So there are some
collapsing that way.
Then the supernodes
are these combinations
where we say, OK, you
had a particular purpose,
a particular diagnosis,
a particular set
of interventions, a
particular set of procedures.
And again, we list all
possible combinations of those,
and then that sequence
represents your sequence.
These are aggregated
into supernodes.
That represents
your visit sequence,
and then these super
pairs are this hack
to let you look two steps
back in the Markov chain.
And so they wind up with
about 3,500 different
of these super pair nodes.
So it is combinatorial,
but it's not terribly
combinatorial in their data.
They then compute the
maximum of the length
of common subsequences between
each pair of visit sequences.
So they're going to
cluster these sequences.
They define a
distance function that
says that the more they
share a common sequence,
the less distant they
are from each other.
And the particular
distance function
they used is the length of
each sequence minus twice
the length of the common
subsequence, the longest
common subsequence, which
seems pretty reasonable.
And then hierarchical clustering
into distinct subgroups,
they came up with 31 groups
for this group of patients,
and here they are.
And what you see is
that some of them
don't differ a whole
lot from each other.
So, for example,
these two differ only
in that the patient got some
medication and diuretics
in one case and just that
medication in the other case.
So these are-- it is a
hierarchical cluster,
and the things lower
down in the clustering
are probably fairly
close to each other.
Nevertheless, what
they're able to do,
then, is to estimate
a transition matrix
among these supernode
pair states,
and they can look at
different trajectories
depending on the degree
of support for the data.
So you can set
different thresholds
on how many cases have to be
in a particular state in order
for you to take transitions to
or from that state seriously.
One of the critiques I
would make of the study
is that they had way too little
data, and so many of the groups
that they came up
with had relatively
small numbers of patients in
them, which is unfortunate.
Now, once you have these
transition matrices,
then you can say, OK,
for cluster 29, which
was this cluster, so
there were a grand total
of 14 patients in this cluster.
They were all at chronic
kidney disease stage
4, so quite severe.
They were all hypertensive.
They were all on ACE
inhibitors and statins,
and everybody in that group
had that categorization.
So if you look there
then you can say, OK,
for all the things we
know about that patient,
what are the probabilistic
relationships between them?
And what we find is that--
man, I can't read these.
So these nodes
imply other nodes,
and the strength of the arrows
is proportional to their width.
And so this is a
representation of everything
that we've learned
about that cluster,
but remember, only
from those 14 patients.
So I'm not sure I would
take this to the bank
and rely on it too intensely.
But they then, by
hand, abstract it
and say, well, let's look at
an interpretation of this.
And so if they look
in typical patterns
that they see in
that cluster, they
say, hmm, we see an
office visit in which
the patient is on
these medications
and has these procedures.
Then they're hospitalized.
Then there's
another-- let's see.
No, I'm sorry.
Yeah, yellow node
is an office visit.
So they're hospitalized.
They then get an
education visit,
so that's typically with the
nurse or nurse practitioner
to explain to them what
they ought to be doing.
They have another hospital--
they have another office visit.
They have a hospital visit.
They have another hospital
visit, and then they die.
So that, unfortunately,
is a not atypical pattern
that you see in patients who
are at a pretty severe state
of chronic kidney disease.
And we don't know
from this diagram
how long this process
takes to take place.
So I have some questions.
There are a lot of subgroups.
Some of them were fairly
similar to others.
They have between 10 and 158
patients in each subgroup.
So I would feel
much better if they
had between 1,000 and
15,000 or something
patients in each group, or
150,000 patients in each group.
I would feel much more
believing in the representations
that they found.
And the other
problem is that even
within an individual
subgroup, you can
find very different patterns.
So, for example, here is a
pattern where, again, a person
has a couple of office visits.
They go to the hospital.
Or they go to the hospital
twice with slightly different--
yes.
So this person at this point
is in acute kidney injury.
So you can get there either
directly from the office visit
or from an earlier
hospitalization,
and then they die.
And so this is part
of that pattern.
But here's another pattern mined
from exactly the same subgroup.
Now, this subgroup has
122 patients in it,
so there's a little
bit more heterogeneity.
But what you see here
is that a patient
is going back and forth between
education visits and doctor's
visits, back and
forth between doctors
visits and hospitalizations,
then a hospitalization, then
another hospitalization,
but they're surviving.
So it's a little bit tricky,
but I think this is a good idea,
but there are
probably improvements
that are possible on
the technique that's
being used here.
And, of course, much more
data would be very helpful
in order to really
delineate what's
going on in these patients.
Here's a similar idea
that I was involved.
Jeff Klann did his
PhD at Regenstrief,
which is a very well-known,
very early adopter
of computerized information
systems in Indiana.
And so what he started
off-- and he said, hmm.
You know the Amazon
recommendation system
that says you just
bought this camera lends,
and other people who bought
this camera lens also
bought a cleaning kit
and a battery that goes
with that camera, and so on?
So he said, why don't
we apply that same idea
to medical orders?
And so he took the record of
all the orders at Regenstrief,
and he basically
built an approximation
to the Amazon recommendation
system that said,
hey, other doctors who have
ordered the following set
of tests have also ordered
this additional test
that you didn't order.
Maybe you should
consider doing it.
Or conversely, other doctors who
have ordered this set of tests
have never ordered this
other one in addition.
And so are you sure
you really need it?
So that was the idea.
And what he did was
he focused on four
different clinical issues.
So one of them was an
emergency department visit
for back pain, pregnancy,
so labor and delivery,
hypertension in the
urgent visit clinic--
so the urgent visit clinic
is one of these lower-level
non-emergency department,
cheaper, lower level of care,
but still urgent care kinds
of clinics that many hospitals
have established in order to try
to keep people who are not that
sick out of the emergency
department and in this
lower-intensity clinic--
and hypertension, and
high blood pressure,
and then altered mental state
in the intensive care unit.
So people in the ICU
are often medicated,
and they become wacko,
and so this is trying
to take care of such patients.
They used three years
of encountered data
from Regenstrief.
And for each domain,
they limited themselves
to the 40 most frequent orders,
and, again, low granularity.
So, for example,
drug, but not the dose
of the drug for
medications, and the 10 most
frequent comorbidities or
co-occurring diagnoses.
So this is an example of wisdom
of the crowd kind of approach
that says, well, what
your colleagues do
is probably a good
representation of what
you ought to be doing.
Now, what's an obvious
pitfall of this approach?
I'm just checking to
see if you're awake.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Just reinforce
whatever's [INAUDIBLE]..
PETER SZOLOVITS: Yeah,
if they're all bozos,
they're going to train
you to be a bozo too.
And there's a lot
of stuff in medicine
that is not very
well-supported by evidence,
where, in fact, people
have developed traditions
of doing things a certain way
that may not be the right way
to do it.
And this just reinforces that.
On the other hand, it
probably does reduce variance
in the sense that we talked
about at the beginning.
And so, as a result, it may
be a reasonable approach,
if you're willing to
tolerate some exceptions.
My favorite story is
Semmelweiss figured out
that having a baby in
a hospital in Vienna
was extremely dangerous
for the mother,
because they would
die of what was
called "child bed fever," which
was basically an infection.
And Semmelweiss figured
out that maybe there
was-- this was before Pasteur.
But he figured out
that maybe there
was something that was being
transmitted from one woman
to the next that was causing
this child bed fever,
and, of course, he was right.
And he did an experiment,
where on his maternity ward,
he had all of the
younger doctors
wash their hands with some
sort of alcohol or something
to kill whatever they
were transmitting.
And their death rate
from this child bed fever
dropped to almost 0.
And he went to his colleagues
and he said, hey, guys, we
could really make the
world a better place
and stop killing women.
And they looked at
him, and they said,
you know, these hands
heal, they don't kill.
Many of them were upper
class or noblemen who
had gone into this profession.
The idea that somehow they were
responsible for transmitting
what turns out to
be bacteria was just
a non-starter for them.
And Semmelweiss wound
up ending his days
in a mental institution,
because he went nuts.
He was unable to
change practice even
though he had done an experiment
to demonstrate that it worked.
So this is a case where
the wisdom of the crowd
was not so good and
led to bad outcomes.
So like Amazon's
recommendation system,
it automates the learning
of decision support rules.
And what's attractive about
this is that because it's
induced from real data, it tends
to deal with more complex cases
than the sort of simple,
stereotypical cases
for which people can
develop guidelines,
for example, where
they can anticipate
what's going to happen
in various circumstances.
So he used the Bayesian
networking model
that used diagnoses possible
orders and evidence, which
is the results from orders
that were already completed.
There's a system out of
University of Pittsburgh,
called Tetrad, that implements
a nice version of something
called Greedy
Equivalent Search, which
is a faster way of
searching through the space
of Bayesian networks for
an appropriate network that
represents your data.
So it's a highly
combinatorial problem,
and the cleverness in this
is that it figures out
classes of Bayesian networks
that, by definition, would
fit the data equally well.
And it does it by class rather
than by individual network,
and so it gets a nice
combinatorial reduction.
And what Jeff found is, for
example, in the pregnancy
network, these
are the nodes that
correspond to
various interventions
and various conditions.
And this is the Bayesian network
that best fits that data.
It's reasonably complicated.
Here are some others.
This is for the emergency
department case.
So you see that you have things
like chest pain and abdominal
pain presenting
diagnoses, and then
you have various
procedures, like an abdomen
CT, or a pelvic CT, or
a chest CT, or a head
CT, or a basic metabolic
panel, et cetera,
and this gives you the
probabilistic relationships
between them.
And so what they were able to
do is to take this Bayesian
network representation,
and then if you
lay a particular patient's
data on that representation,
that corresponds to fixing
the value of certain nodes.
And then you do Bayesian
inference to figure out
the probabilities of
the unobserved nodes,
and you recommend the highest
probability interventions
that have not yet been done.
So it's a little bit
like, if you remember,
we talked about
sequential diagnosis.
This is a little
bit in that spirit,
but it's a much more complicated
Bayesian network model rather
than a naive-based model.
And so the interface
looks like this.
You have-- it's called the
Iterative Treatment Suggestions
algorithm, and it
shows the doctor
that these are the
problems of the patient,
and the current orders, and
the probability that you
might ask to have any
one of these orders done.
And what they're able to show is
that this does reasonably well.
Obviously, it wouldn't
have been published if they
hadn't been able to show that.
And so what you see is that, for
example, the next order that's
done in an inpatient pregnancy
using this Bayesian network
formalism has a position of
about fourth on the list.
So their criterion for
judging this algorithm
is, is it raising the
things that people actually
do too high on the
list of the recommended
list, on the recommended
set of actions
that you consider doing?
And you see that it's
fourth, on average,
in inpatient pregnancy,
about sixth in the ICU,
about sixth in the
emergency department,
and about fifth in the
urgent care clinic.
So that's pretty
good, because that
means that even if you're
looking at an iPhone,
there's enough screen
real estate that it'll
be on the so-called first
page of Google hits,
which is the only thing
people ever pay attention to.
And, in fact, they can
show that the average list
position corresponds to the
order rank by frequency,
but that their model does a
reasonably good job of keeping
you within the first 10 or
so for much of this range.
I'm going to shift gears again.
So Adam Right, you've met.
He was discussant in one
of our earlier classes.
And Adam's been very active
in trying to deploy decision
support systems.
And he had an interesting
episode back in--
when was this--
2016.
So it must have been
a little before 2016.
He went to demonstrate this
great decision support system
that they had implemented
at the Brigham,
and he put in a fake case where
an alert should have gone off
for a patient who has been on
a particular drug for more than
a year and needs to have their
thyroid stimulating hormone
measured in order to check
for a potential side effect
of long-term use of amiodarone,
as well as to have their--
ALT is a liver test,
liver enzyme test.
So they needed both
of those tests.
He was demonstrating
this wonderful system.
He put in a fake patient
who had these conditions,
and the alert didn't go off.
So he goes, hmm,
what's going on?
And they went back,
and they discovered
that in 2009 the system's
internal code for amiodarone
had been changed
from 40 to 70-99.
Who knows why?
But the rule logic in
the system was never
updated to reflect this change.
And so, in fact, if
you look at the history
of the use of amiodarone--
by the way, it's an
interesting graph.
The blue dots are weekdays, and
the black dots are weekends.
So not a lot goes on in the
hospital during the weekend.
But what you see is that--
I don't know what happened
before about the end of 2009.
They probably weren't running
that rule or something.
But what you see is sort
of a gradual increase
in the use of this rule, and
then you see a long decrease
from 2010 up through 2013 when
they discovered this problem.
Now, why a decrease?
I mean, it's not a
sudden jump to 0.
And the reason was
that this came about--
first of all, it
came about gradually,
because the people who had had
this drug before that change
in the software had
gotten the old code, which
was still triggering the rule.
It's just that as time went
on, more and more people
who needed the test had gotten
the drug with its new code.
And with that new code, it was
no longer triggering the rule.
And then this is the point at
which they discovered the bug,
and then they fixed it.
Of course, it came
right back up again.
Oh.
Well, I'll talk about some
of the others as well.
So this was the amiodarone case.
So it fell suddenly, as
some patients were taken off
the drug and others were started
with this new internal code.
And as I said, the alert
logic was fixed back in 2013.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So I don't know
how hospital IT systems work,
and it might vary
from place to place.
But is there ever a notion
of like this computer needs
to be updated for the
software, but that one already
got updated?
Or are they all synced
up so that they all
get updated at the same time?
PETER SZOLOVITS:
They tend to all get
updated at the same time.
There are disasters
that have happened
in that updating process.
Famously, the Beth Israel was
down for about three days.
Their computer
system just crashed.
And what they discovered is that
they had this very complicated
network in which there were
cyclic dependencies in order
to boot up different systems.
So some system had
to be up in order
to let some other
system be up, which
had to be up in order to
let the first system be up.
And, of course, in
normal operation,
they never take down
the whole system,
and so nobody had discovered
this until there was--
Cisco screwed them.
There was some fix in the
routers that caused everything
to crash, and then they
couldn't bring it back up again.
And so that was a big panic.
John Halamka, who's
the CIO there,
is a former student of mine.
And after this all
played out, I asked John,
so what's the first thing
you did when this happened?
And he said, I sent a
couple of panel trucks
down to the Staples warehouse
to buy pads of paper,
which is pretty smart.
So here's another example.
This is lead screening.
And so this was a case where
there is a lead screening
rule for two-year-olds.
There is also one for one-,
three-, and four-year-olds.
And there was no change in
screening for one-, three-,
and four-year-olds, but the
screening for two-year-olds
went from 300 or 400 a day down
to 0 for several years before
they noticed it, and then went
back up to the previous level.
And they never did quite
figure out what happened here,
but something added two
incomplete clauses to the rule
having to do with gender
and smoking status.
But the clauses were incomplete,
and so they were actually
looking for the case of neither
the gender nor the smoking
status having been specified.
So smoking status
for a two-year-old,
you could imagine, is
not often specified,
but gender typically is.
And so the rule never
fired because of that,
and they have no idea how
these changes were made.
There's a complicated
logging system
that logs all the changes, and
it crashed and lost its logging
data.
And it's a just so story.
Chlamydia screen--
this was human error.
And so they wound
up-- they found
this very quickly, because they
had a two-month-old boy who
had numerous duplicate
reminders, including
suggestions for
mammograms, pap smears,
pneumococcal vaccination,
and cholesterol
screening, and a
suggestion to start
the patient on various meds.
So this was just a human
error in revising the rule,
and that one they
found pretty quickly.
So that's amusing.
But what's interesting is these
guys went on to say, well, how
could we monitor for this
in some ongoing fashion?
And so they said, well,
there's this notion
of change point detection,
which is an interesting machine
learning problem, again.
And so they said, well, suppose
we built a dynamic linear model
that includes seasonality,
because we have
to deal with the fact
that a lot of stuff
happens Monday through
Friday and nothing happens
on weekends?
And so they created
a model that says
that your output is some
function, f, of your inputs,
plus some noise.
The noise is Gaussian with
some variance, capital V,
and that x evolves according
to some evolution that
says it depends on the
previous value of x,
plus some other noise,
which is also Gaussian.
So that's the general sort of
time series modeling approach
that people often take.
And then they said, well, we
have to deal with seasonality.
So what we're going to do is
define a period, namely a week,
and then we're going
to separate out
the states on different
days of the week
in order to give us the ability
to model that seasonality.
I worked on a different
project having
to do with outbreak detection
for infectious diseases,
and there the
periodicity was a year,
because things like the
flu come in yearly cycles
rather than in weekly cycles.
And so that idea
is pretty common.
And then they built this
multiprocess dynamic linear
model that says,
basically, imagine
that our data is
being generated by one
of a set of these
dynamic linear models.
And so we have an
additional state variable
at each time that says
which of the models
is in control to generate
the data at this point.
And so if you have the set of
observations up to some time,
t, then you can
compute the probability
that model i is driving the
generator at this point.
And so you can have
three basic models.
You can have a
model that says it's
a stable model, in
other words, what
you expect is the steady state.
So that would be the normal
weekly variation in volume
for any of these alerts.
You can have a model which
is an additive outlier.
So that's something that says,
all of a sudden, something
happened, like that
chlamydia screen
or one of the other things
that had a very quick blip.
Or you can have a
level shift change,
like the change that
happened when the screening
rules or the alert
rule for amiodarone
stopped firing, because
it went from one level
to a very different level
over a period of a relatively
short period of time.
And then what you can do is
calculate the probability
of any of these models being
in control at the next time,
and that's called the
change point score.
And you can calculate this from
the data that you're given.
And of course, they
have tons of data.
It's a big hospital and
lots of these alerts go on.
And if you plot this, there's
the data for a time series.
So you see the weekly variation.
But what you see is
that the probability
of the steady behavior is quite
high except at certain points
where it all of a sudden dips.
And so those are places where
you suspect that something
interesting is going on.
And similarly, the probability
of a temporary offset
goes up at these various points,
and the probability of a level
shift goes up at this point.
And you can see
that, indeed, there
is a level shift
from essentially 0 up
to this periodic behavior in
the original data sequence.
And so they actually implemented
this in the hospital,
and so now you get
not just alerts,
but you get
meta-alerts that say,
this kid ought to be screened
for their lead levels,
but also the lead
level screening rule
hasn't fired as often as
we expected it to fire.
Yeah, so there are
a lot of details
in the paper that you can
look up, if you're interested.
And what they find
is that, if you
look at the area under the
delay false positive rate curve,
so you're trading off how
long it takes to be certain
that one of these conditions has
occurred versus how often you
cry wolf, and you see
that their algorithm does
much better than a
bunch of other things
that they tried it against,
which are earlier attempts
to do this.
And these are all highly
statistically significant,
so they got a nice
paper out of it.
In the remaining
time, I wanted to talk
about a number of other
issues that really
have to do with workflow.
So we've talked about
alerting, but there
are an interesting
set of studies
about how these alerting
systems actually work.
So there was a cool idea from
the Beth Israel Deaconess
Hospital here in Boston
where they said, well,
what we really need to
do is to escalate alerts.
So, for example, it's
quite typical in a hospital
that, if you're a doctor and
you have a patient who you have
just sent their
blood to the lab,
and let's say there serum
potassium comes back as 7 or 8,
that patient is at high risk of
going into cardiac arrhythmia
and dying.
And so your pager, in
those days, goes off,
and you read this text
message that says,
Mr. Jones has a
serum potassium of 8.
You'd better look in on him.
So what they did
was very clever.
They said, well, the problem is
busy doctors might ignore this.
And so we'll then start
a countdown timer.
And we'll say, did Dr.
Smith actually come and look
at Mr. Jones within 20 minutes?
And if the answer
is no, then they
send the page to the
doctor's boss that says,
hey, we sent this guy a
page, and within 20 minutes
he didn't look in
on the patient.
And then they start
another timer.
And they say, if that boss
doesn't respond within an hour,
then they send a page to
the head of the hospital
saying, you're her
infectious disease people
are doing a lousy job,
because they're not--
or in this case, you're
endocrine people, or whatever,
are doing a lousy job,
because they're not
responding to these alerts.
Now, how do you think
the doctors liked this?
Not much.
And there is a real
problem with overalerting.
And there is no
general rule that
says, how often can you bug
the head of the hospital
with an alert like this before
he or she just says, well,
turn off the damn thing,
I don't want to see these?
And clearly, if you set the
thresholds at different places,
you get different results.
So, for example, I remember
Tufts implemented a system
like this back in the 1980s,
but they would send a page
on every order where any of
the lab results were abnormal,
and that was way too much.
Because a lot of these
tests generate 20 results.
Normal is defined as the
95% confidence interval.
What are the chances
that out of 20 tests,
which aren't really independent,
but if they were, one of them
would be pretty guaranteed
to be out of range
for most of the patients?
And so basically every
test generated an alert
to the doctor.
And the doctors did
threaten to kill
the people who had
implemented the system,
and it got turned off.
A system like this, if
you set the threshold
to be not abnormal, but
life-threateningly abnormal,
and if you set the
rate and the time
durations such that it's
reasonable for people
to respond to it, then
maybe it can be acceptable.
When we did this project on
looking at how an emergency
department could anticipate
a flood of patients
because it looked like
flu season was starting,
for example, the
question we asked is,
how many false alarms a
month can you guys tolerate?
And they thought about it.
And the ED docs got together
and said, three times a month
you can cry wolf,
because we really
want to know when
it actually happens.
And we'd rather be prepared,
and we can tolerate a 10% error
rate on this prediction.
But I don't know what
it is in this domain.
Another interesting study was--
it's become quite popular.
I got a bunch of
emails from my doctor
today, because I had ordered
a refill on some prescription,
and he wanted to know how it's
going, and blah, blah, blah.
So the BI asked the question,
what fraction of those messages
are never read by the
patients that they're sent to?
Which is an important
question, because if you're
relying on that mode
of communication
as part of your workflow,
you'd like it to be 0.
It turned out only to be 3%,
which is remarkably good.
That means that most people
are actually paying attention
to those kinds of messages.
Then I wanted to say a few
words about the importance
of communication
and then finish up
by mentioning some so
far failed attempts
at really good integration of
all different data sources.
So as I said, the
BI started in 1994
with a system that
said, if you're
taking a renally-excreted
or a nephrotoxic drug,
then we're going to
warn people if there
is a rising creatinine
level, which
is an indication that
your kidneys are not
functioning so well.
Because, of course, if the
drug is renally excreted,
that means that if your kidneys
are not excreting things
at the rate they're
supposed to, you're
going to wind up building up
the amount of drug in your body,
and that can become toxic.
So they saw a 21-hour,
so almost a full day,
reduction in response time
from the medical staff
given these alerts versus
what happened before.
That's remarkable.
I mean, saving a
day in responding
to a condition like
this is really quite
an impressive
result. And they also
saw, in terms of
clinical outcome,
that the risk of
renal impairment
was reduced to about half of
the preintervention level.
So that earlier
response actually
was saving people's
kidney function
by getting people to
intervene earlier.
I found it interesting
they said 44% of doctors
found these alerts helpful,
28% found them annoying,
but 65% of them
wanted them continued
to be used in a survey.
Enrico Carrera is
one of my heroes.
He used to be in the UK.
He's now in Australia.
And he had this very deep
insight back in the 1980s.
He said, you know,
all you computer guys
who are treading on
this medical field
think that all of the action
is about decision-making,
but it's not.
All of the action is
really about communication,
that health care is
basically a team sport.
And unless we spend
much more time
studying what goes
on in communication,
we're going to miss the boat.
And then mostly, we didn't
pay any attention to him,
but he's kept at it.
So he said, well, how big
is the communication space?
So he cited a 1985 study
that said that about 50%
of requests for information
are ones that people
ask their colleague
for versus 26%
that they look up
in their own notes.
So if a doctor is on rounds,
walks into a patient's room
and says, I want to know has
this guy's temperature been
going up or down, a quarter of
the time he'll look at notes.
And half the time, he'll
turn to the nurse and say,
is this patient's
temperature going up or down?
So he says that's interesting.
Paul Tang did a study
in the '90s that
said that in a clinic,
about 60% of the time
is spent talking among the
staff, not doing anything else.
Enrico and one of his
colleagues said that almost 100%
of non-patient
record information,
in other words, the thing
that's not in the written health
record, is done by talking.
That's almost tautological,
because where else would you
get it?
And then Charlie Saffron at the
BI did a time and motion study
and was looking at, I think,
nursing behavior, and saying
that about half their time was
face-to-face communication,
about 10% with electronic
medical records,
and also a lot of email,
and voicemail, and paper
reminders as ways of
communicating among people.
So this was a study looking at--
this is that 1998 study
by Colera and Tombs.
And they're looking at
a consultant, the house
officer, another consultant.
These are British
titles, because this
was done in Australia--
a nurse, et cetera.
And they say, OK,
among hospital staff--
I think this was in
one shift, I believe,
I should have had
that on the slide--
this is the number of pages
that they sent and received.
So they range from
0 up to about 4.
The number of telephone
calls made and received--
this ranges from 0 up to 13.
Oh, here's the length
of observation.
So this was over a period
of about three hours
for each of these patients.
And this is the total
number of events.
So think about it.
In 3 and 1/2 hours, the
senior house officer
had 24 distinct communication
events happen to that person.
So that means, what,
that's like 7--
yeah, like 7 an hour.
So that's like 1 every
10 minutes, roughly.
So it's an interrupt-driven
kind of environment.
Here's one particular
subject that they looked at,
three and a quarter
hours of observation.
This person spent 86%
of their time talking.
31% were taken up
with 28 interruptions.
So even the interruptions
were being interrupted.
25% were multitasking with
two or more conversations.
87%, face-to-face or
on a phone or a pager.
So most of that is talk time.
And 13% dealing with
computers and patient notes.
So the communication
function is really important.
And I don't have anything
profound to say about it other
than I'll put up a pointer
to some of these papers.
But the kinds of things
they're considering
are, well, we could
introduce new channels,
or new types of messages, or
new communication policies
that say, you know
you may not interrupt
the person who's
taking care of patients
while they're doing it,
or something like that.
And then moving from synchronous
to asynchronous methods,
like voicemail, or
email, or Slack,
or some modern
communication mechanism.
Let me skip by these.
Next to the last
topic, quickly, how
do you keep from
dropping the ball?
So there are a lot
of analyses that
say that the biggest
mistakes in health care
are made not because somebody
makes the wrong decision,
but it's because somebody
fails to make a decision.
They just forget
about something.
They don't follow-up on
something that they ought to.
The patient is going along,
and you think everything's OK,
and you don't deal with it.
So inspired partly by
that escalation of pagers
that I read about
at the Beth Israel,
I said, well, this sounds
like what we really need
is a workflow engine that's
approximately a discrete event
simulator.
So has anybody built a discrete
events simulator in this class?
It's a fairly standard sort
of programming problem,
and it's useful in simulating
all kinds of things
that involve discrete events.
And the idea is that
you have a timeline,
and you run down the
timeline, and you
execute the next
activity that comes up.
And that activity
does something.
It sends an email, or it shoots
a rocket, or whatever field
you're doing the simulation in.
But most importantly, what
it does is-- the last thing
it does is it schedules
something else to happen later
in the timeline.
So, for example, for something
that happens once a day, when
it happens, the task
that runs schedules it
to happen again the next day.
And that means that it's going
to be continually operating
all the time.
So the idea I had was that what
you'd like to do is to say,
if at some time, t,
I have a task that
says do x or asks
z to do y, or both,
then the last thing
should be at some time
in the future schedule another
task that says, is y done?
And if not, then go notify
somebody or go remind somebody.
And as far as I
know, no hospital
and no electronic record system
has any capability like this,
but I still think
it's a terrific idea.
And then I wanted to
finish with a pointer
to a problem that is
still very much with us.
So in 1994, some
colleagues and I
wrote this thing we called
"The Guardian Angel Manifesto."
And the idea was that we
should engage patients
more in their own
care, because they
can keep track of
a lot of the things
that systems didn't do a very
good job of keeping track of.
And the idea was that you would
have a computational process
that would start off at the
time your parents conceived you
and run until your
autopsy after you died.
And during this
time, it would be
responsible for collecting
all the relevant health care
data about you.
So it would be your
electronic medical record,
but it would also be active.
So it would help you
communicate with your providers.
It would help educate you
about any conditions you have.
It would remind
you about things.
It would schedule stuff
for you, et cetera.
So this was a nice
science fiction vision.
And in the mid-2000s,
Adam Bosworth,
who was a VP of
Google, came to me.
And he said, you know,
I read your thing.
It's a good idea.
I'm going to do it.
So Google started up this thing
called Google Health, which
was more focused on being
at least the personal health
record.
They did a pilot with 1,600
people at Cleveland Clinic,
and then they went
public as a beta.
And three years
later, they killed it.
And they had a
bunch of partners.
So they had Allscripts,
and Beth Israel,
and Blue Cross of Massachusetts,
and the Cleveland Clinic,
and CVS, and so on.
So they did their job
of trying to connect
to a bunch of important players.
But, of course, they
didn't have everybody.
And so, for example,
I, of course,
immediately signed
up for an account,
and the only company that I had
ever dealt with out of that set
was Walgreens, where
I had bought a skin
cream one time for a skin rash.
And so my total medical
record consisted
of a skin rash
and a cream that I
had bought to take care of it--
not very helpful.
And so nobody, other
than these partners,
could enter data
automatically, which
meant that you had to be even
more anal compulsive than I
am in order to
sit there and type
in my entire medical
history into the system,
especially, because if I did so,
nobody would ever look at it.
Because if I go to
my doctor and say,
hey, Doc, here's the Google
URL for my medical record,
and here's the password by
which you can access it,
what do you think are the
odds that they're actually
going to look?
AUDIENCE: 0.
PETER SZOLOVITS: 0.
So the thing was an
absolute abject failure.
And people keep trying it.
And so far, nobody has
figured out how to do it,
but it's still a good idea.
With that, we'll
stop on workflow.